<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-04-23T20:20:11+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Labour Nexus</title><subtitle>Labour Nexus is a campaign force to unite our party, create an environment for constructive discourse and bring Labour to Downing Street.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Labour: What do we all have in common?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blogs/2021/04/14/labour-what-do-we-all-have-in-common.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Labour: What do we all have in common?" /><published>2021-04-14T00:00:53+00:00</published><updated>2021-04-14T00:00:53+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blogs/2021/04/14/labour-what-do-we-all-have-in-common</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blogs/2021/04/14/labour-what-do-we-all-have-in-common.html">&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/allhaveincommon/thumbnail.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%; height: auto;&quot; alt=&quot;Tony Blair at Downing Street on the left, Keir Starmer's New Leadership speech in the center, Jeremy Corbyn on the right&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image-bottom&quot;&gt;
    Tony Blair at Downing Street on the left, Keir Starmer's New Leadership speech in the center, Jeremy Corbyn on the right 
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you know that Labour, the Tories, the SNP, the Liberal Democrats, the Greens and Plaid Cymru all say that they support, in these exact words, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL7AdbhgdgEN7mJKaEP_5IN-RxmjqPNpOW&quot;&gt;“fairer society”?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, these opposing political parties also agree that we need investment in the NHS, policies to create equality of opportunity, support for small businesses, measures to end child poverty, measures to end regional inequality, more police on the streets, devolution, social mobility, better schools, investment in the railways, anti-racism legislation, and measures to tackle the climate crisis, including an expansion of green energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the reason why there seems to be so much overlap is because these are the clichés of British politics — the buzzwords that frame the debate and form the basic checklist that governmental success or failure is measured against. The fact that all the major parties talk about them does not actually mean those parties have much in common with one another. Though the shared buzzwords make it possible to argue that all six main parties are really on the same side and just disagree about how to achieve their shared goals, this interpretation would be hopelessly shallow and naïve. This is because, beneath the surface, there really is little that unites them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people believe that the Labour Party’s internal politics are similar. ‘Thatcherite neoliberals’ and ‘hard-left cranks’ might share common buzzwords and an enmity to the Tories, the argument goes, but beneath the surface their beliefs are basically incompatible. Those who make that argument believe that the idea that all Labour members are allies is just as shallow and naïve as the idea that the Tories and the Greens are really on the same side because both talk about creating a “fairer society” and building more wind turbines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This perception is not limited to factionalist hardliners. Labour Nexus, a small sect of anti-factionalism campaigners who push for more co-operation and good-faith debate, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kw_stapleton_/status/1367916364946636802?s=20&quot;&gt;recently ran a workshop with Young Labour members which found that “no-one was sure what common values or policies united the various factions”&lt;/a&gt;, to the point that everyone at the workshop agreed that ‘I support Labour’ felt like a meaningless statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is sad that so many members believe that nothing unites the party’s traditions, because it is simply not true. The areas of agreement between the Labour factions are far more profound than the superficial overlaps between Labour and other political parties. It is these shared perspectives and values that make it possible that members from different factions could trust each other’s intentions and debate in good faith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at political beliefs, rather than organisations and alliances, the Labour Party is a coalition between five main groups:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Social democrats who support the Third Way pursued under New Labour, believing that capitalism can be reformed, and who focus on social equality and multiculturalism;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Democratic socialists who want the party to focus on supporting working people’s struggle against the ruling class and who believe socialism can be directly established by a Labour government;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Social democrats who reject both the Third Way and directly establishing socialism, instead viewing social democracy as a road to socialism through gradual reforms, and who tend to emphasise the importance of compromise;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Left-wingers who focus particularly on social justice issues and the climate emergency, often inspired by radical politics in America, and who have a distinctive cultural libertarian stance; and&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Self-described social conservatives, whose economic and social views are based around building strong local communities, supporting their inborn social values, and giving more power to local and regional structures.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For convenience, call those who take these stances ‘New Labour’, ‘democratic socialists’, the ‘soft left’, the ‘social justice left’ and ‘Blue Labour’ respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All five agree that the economy should serve the community as a whole, not anyone’s private interests. For New Labour, the way to achieve this is through well-regulated private companies, though with the state managing basic provision like health and education. Democratic socialists share the same goal as New Labour but argue that achieving it requires universal common ownership of enterprise. The soft left agree with New Labour that regulated private companies are appropriate for most goods and services, but they believe that public services like utilities and transport should join health and education in the public sector, and some view creative regulation of private companies as a step towards common ownership in the long term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that all members and factions share the goal of the economy serving the community, not private interests, there is scope for fruitful debate and compromise between the positions favoured by each ideological strand. For instance, policies like John McDonnell’s plan to put workers on boards or the Co-operative Party’s wish to double the size of the co-op sector might be a way to satisfy those who favour regulated private companies and those who prefer common ownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Labour worldview, an economy that serves the community is incompatible with one that serves private interests — it cannot do both. The slogan is “the many, not the few”, rather than ‘the many and the few’. It is certainly not ‘the few, trickling down to the many’. That phrase “the many, not the few” was added to the party’s constitution in 1995 when Tony Blair and the modernisers changed the wording of Clause IV. This foundational statement of New Labour’s beliefs was later taken up by democratic socialists and the social justice left under the leadership of Jeremy Corbyn. It should be a slogan that unites the party, not one that divides it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another point of agreement in Labour is that Britain’s foreign policy should be driven by ideology and values, not merely expediency or ‘strategic objectives’. For the social justice left and most democratic socialists, &lt;a href=&quot;https://labour.org.uk/press/labour-put-social-justice-heart-everything-labour-government-will-new-social-justice-commission/&quot;&gt;it means a Labour government must take an explicitly anti-imperialist stance, supporting oppressed peoples against Western aggression&lt;/a&gt;. For New Labour, it means Britain should align itself with the United States and the EU, and intervene abroad to protect the liberal rules-based international order or liberate people who are living under dictators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the surface, these are markedly different positions, and as the bitter arguments over the Iraq War show, many members see them as irreconcilable. But that shared commitment to a foreign policy driven by principles, not self-interest or pragmatism, means there is common ground between Corbynite anti-imperialism and Blairite Atlanticism. Good-faith debates between these camps about how best to use foreign policy to protect democracy, equality and human rights are possible because there is a shared Labour view that this is what foreign policy is for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, there would be no point debating it with the Tories, because their only focus is on strategic interests; building power and soliciting investment. Theresa May, the last Prime Minister who had the opportunity to pursue a foreign policy not defined by COVID, spent time sucking up to both Donald Trump and Xi Jinping, a racist liar and a genocidal autocrat. She saw no need to confront either man about his behaviour, nor did she accept that there was anything contradictory about simultaneously aligning Britain with two world powers that were locked in a trade war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Liberal Democrats attempted a hilarious rhetorical backflip in their 2019 manifesto, claiming that their foreign policy would support “our strategic international objectives on gender equality, climate change and the environment, human rights”, etc. How can a country possibly have ‘strategic objectives’ on human rights. What does that even mean? As per usual, they have started from a Tory base — the assumption that foreign policy should be based on national self-interest and strategic objectives — and tried to build across to something resembling Labour values. As for the SNP’s foreign policy plan, with its emphasis on the Nordic countries, the Arctic and the EU, their international approach is merely an extension of the regionalist agenda they push at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, everyone knows that the SNP are regionalists. Scottish nationalism is the SNP’s main ‘thing’ in the eyes of the public. Labour’s is probably better investment in public services. Everyone knows that Labour would spend more on schools, right? But actually, it goes deeper than that. Labour is the only party that believes the welfare state is not about providing a minimum safety net. For Labour, it is about improving the lives of everyone, both working class and middle-class, so that no-one ever needs such a safety net. The welfare state should be a regular fixture in everyone’s lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NHS has evolved from a partisan project of the left that the Tories opposed into a cliché of British politics that every party claims to support, and this is because the Labour Party is right: welfare for all is a mark of a civilised society. Blue Labour’s belief in strong civic institutions and social solidarity, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2001/may/23/labour.tonyblair&quot;&gt;New Labour’s investment in public libraries and children’s centres&lt;/a&gt;, and the soft left’s calls for more statutory maternity pay all reflect a deep shared commitment to welfare for the many, not the few — welfare not just for those who are struggling, but for those who are doing well but want to do better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a school of thought that says Labour’s ‘centrist’ wing, meaning &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Labour&quot;&gt;New Labour&lt;/a&gt; and sometimes the soft left, are more like social liberals than socialists. This is emphatically not true. Social liberals, the ostensibly centre-left wing of the Liberal Democrats, agree with John Locke that “the end of law is not to abolish or restrain”, and they are accordingly very cynical about the power of the state to improve people’s lives directly. Social democrats, who are part of the socialist movement, are not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Labour&quot;&gt;New Labour&lt;/a&gt; and the soft left want to abolish poverty; democratic socialists want to abolish excessive wealth and capitalism; the social justice left want to abolish racism, homophobia, etc; Blue Labour want to abolish commodification — but social liberals do not believe the state can abolish any of these things at all. It is an insipid ideology that is only similar to the Labour right in the most empty, superficial way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most importantly, Labour is about supporting hard-working people’s right to reap what they have sown. Many democratic socialists embrace a Marxist analysis of profit and alienation, and argue that workers should be directly entitled to the value they create whilst working. The social justice left point out that people of colour and disabled people often have to work the hardest and emphasise that they must not be excluded from the rewards. Blue Labour have a particular focus on hard work as a social good, and as a source of meaning for the individual. The soft left sees hard-working people as held back by a system that is rigged against them, and want to level the playing field. New Labour emphasise that both the working class and the middle class work hard, and so both classes deserve better in exchange.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not simply an extension of the right to equality of opportunity, which is something that everyone in British politics claims to back. It is about the common people’s right to the riches their work has created. Everyone in Labour, from Marxists to Third Way social democrats, is united by their commitment to the principle that everyone is entitled to the full fruits of their labour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since its foundation, Labour has been a broad church. It is not ideologically uniform and unity will never mean all of its members agreeing on the same policies — and nor should it. The party should be a coalition in which campaign groups, members, MPs, councillors, activists and academics feel able to openly disagree about policies and electoral tactics without that stopping them being allies. Everyone in Labour is on the same side, and diversity of opinion is our strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Productive pluralism is only possible if the ties that bind us together are not merely bland and superficial. If nothing unites Labour beyond a vague commitment to ‘everyone having a good standard of living’ or ‘no person having to face poverty or discrimination’, then ultimately the party stands for nothing more than better management; doing what every other party says they would do, but doing it more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, Labour is not condemned to this fate, because its differing ideological strands have distinctive and specific shared perspectives. Finding common ground for debate is not enough to fix factionalism — but it is an important place to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our party is more than just ‘not the Tories’ and there really are things that we all have in common. That is a starting place not only for ending factionalism but for building a positive, compelling policy programme. That means it’s about time we reminded ourselves of it. Let’s clear out the insipid buzzwords that every party claims, put the values that we all share front and centre, and let’s take them into the next election as a united party with a clear vision.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kerry Stapleton</name></author><category term="Blogs" /><summary type="html">Tony Blair at Downing Street on the left, Keir Starmer's New Leadership speech in the center, Jeremy Corbyn on the right</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/posts/allhaveincommon/thumbnail.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/posts/allhaveincommon/thumbnail.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Should Labour be pro business? - A breakdown on the issue.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/issues/2021/04/05/is-labour-pro-business.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Should Labour be pro business? - A breakdown on the issue." /><published>2021-04-05T00:00:53+00:00</published><updated>2021-04-05T00:00:53+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/issues/2021/04/05/is-labour-pro-business</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/issues/2021/04/05/is-labour-pro-business.html">&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/stock/sky-scraper.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%; height: auto;&quot; alt=&quot;A skyscraper in London&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image-bottom&quot;&gt;
    A skyscraper in London  |  Credit Pixabay
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is the first in Labour Nexus’ series considering both sides of contentious arguments. These articles will not support one side over the other. Rather, they will operate as an easily accessible, bitesize articulation of the pertinent arguments over contemporary issues. In recent weeks, there has been much debate over &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.msn.com/en-gb/money/homeandproperty/keir-starmer-the-labour-party-are-more-than-pro-business/vi-BB1f7Pwr?pfr=1&quot;&gt;Keir Starmer’s ‘pro-business’ stance&lt;/a&gt;. Here, the arguments for and against such a stance will be discussed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pro-business-is-contrary-to-labour-values&quot;&gt;Pro-business is contrary to Labour values&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The argument against this pro-business stance is that it runs contrary to the fundamental principles and aims of the Labour Party. Why, it has been asked, should the Labour Party support business when our primary aim is to support workers. This argument finds weight in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keir_Hardie&quot;&gt;Keir Hardie’s&lt;/a&gt; articulations at the start of the 20th century. Hardie proclaimed that “[t]he worker in the workshop is fettered by the thought that outside his workshop gates there are thousands eager and willing to step into his shoes should he be dismissed in consequence of any attempt to improve his position”. It is this unequal relationship between employer and employee that inspired Hardie to create a socialist movement. Without respecting this raison d’etre of the Labour Party, we lose all our principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/probusiness/keirhardie460.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%; height: auto;&quot; alt=&quot;Keir Hardie protesting in Trafalgar Square&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image-bottom&quot;&gt;
    Keir Hardie protesting in Trafalgar Square 
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pro-business is not possible without an anti-worker mentality. The Labour Party should always prioritise the protection of workers rights rather than supporting business. There is great inequality of bargaining power between employers and employees. A contract of employment is often a fixed-form contract, with no room for negotiation. This inability to negotiate places the worker in a poor position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, the working hours and rate of remuneration are often set with only the benefits of the employer in mind. The worker is often economically compelled to accept these employer-favoured benefits, effectively meaning that businesses can impose whatever onerous terms they wish. Secondly, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/4555ae68-75a5-11e6-bf48-b372cdb1043a&quot;&gt;there has been a large increase of zero-hour contracts in recent years&lt;/a&gt;. In law, those on zero-hours contracts are not considered to be employees, rather they fall into the lesser category of workers. This is because there is no mutuality of obligations between employer and employee when the employer is under no obligation to give the worker hours. This classification as a worker grants fewer statutory employment rights than an employee receives. This combination of inequality of bargaining power, and the growing limitation of statutory employment rights in the context of zero-hours contracts, means that the Labour Party should focus on workers rights rather than appease business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A real worry coming out of this pro-business stance is that this represents a genuine departure from the radical policies of the past five years. The manifestos in both &lt;a href=&quot;https://labour.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/labour-manifesto-2017.pdf&quot;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://labour.org.uk/wp-content/uploads/2019/11/Real-Change-Labour-Manifesto-2019.pdf&quot;&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt; had, at the heart of them, the desire to protect the workers (the many) against the interests of businesses (the few). A pro-business stance runs contrary to this. Worse still, there is no evidence that the jeopardising of these principles achieves electability. Not only has Keir Starmer’s approval rating fallen in recent polls, but the Labour Party is also falling further behind the Tories. Therefore, not only is this pro-business stance contrary to Labour values, its justification in terms of electability is flawed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;being-pro-business-is-good-actually&quot;&gt;Being pro-business is good, actually&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/probusiness/tonyblair.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%; height: auto;&quot; alt=&quot;Tony Blair greeting a crowd in 1997&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image-bottom&quot;&gt;
    Tony Blair greeting a crowd in 1997  | Credit: Getty Images
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pro-business approach is compatible with Labour values. Those who say it is not misunderstand the rationale behind an advocation for workers rights. We do not (and should not) support workers rights because workers are more important people than business owners. Rather, we support workers rights because big business is powerful. Owing to this power, the only way to ensure a fair bargain is for the state to provide collective rights. It is this desire to pushback against powerful business that the Labour Party should support small business. Small businesses have the same inequality of bargaining power as workers. For example, farmers who supply supermarkets are often subject to exclusivity clauses and rely on state subsidies to make their industry profitable. A small clothes manufacturer who supplies a large chain will also be subject to these onerous terms, often with the possibility of a unilateral change of contract. In this regard, both small-businesses and workers suffer from the same status as they are both ‘dependent contractors’. This is a term that has been used in arguments for the reform of employment rights. Fundamentally, these small businesses rely on big business to the same extent that workers do. Therefore, we should seek to protect both to the same degree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The argument that we should prioritise the protection of workers rights over those of small businesses fail to understand that it is not a zero-sum game. We can push for stronger rights for both at the same time. Yes, there may be clashes at times between workers’ rights and those of small businesses. For example, a small business may be struggling financially and wish to pay its staff below minimum wage. However, many of the issues faced by small businesses are caused by their subordination to bigger businesses. If we address the issues faced by small business because of big business, it is less likely that small businesses will take advantage of workers. Fundamentally, most small businesses are bastions of the local community who want to be a force for good. Allowing them to flourish outside of the constraints of the onerous conditions imposed by big business can only be a good thing. Therefore, the Labour Party should push for a pro-small business stance alongside its support for workers’ rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of the argument that we are sacrificing Labour values for nothing with a pro-business stance, there are two points to be made. Firstly, small businesses are part of the many. As discussed earlier when considering the ‘dependent contractor’, the connection between small business and workers is closer than the relationship between small business and big business. Therefore, there is no sacrifice of values at all. Secondly, even if there was a sacrifice, a pro-business stance favours electability. Even if it is not showing in the polls currently, policies such as this will present a mosaic of electability by the time the next General Election rolls around. This mosaic can be the foundation upon which we build a successful election strategy. At the end of the day, we cannot achieve anything if Labour is not in government. It is better to sacrifice some principles than none at all if it means we are able to change the country for the better.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Conal Land</name></author><category term="Issues" /><summary type="html">A skyscraper in London | Credit Pixabay</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/stock/sky-scraper.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/stock/sky-scraper.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What barriers do young people feel there are to getting involved with Young Labour?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blogs/2021/04/02/barriers-to-involvement-young-people.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What barriers do young people feel there are to getting involved with Young Labour?" /><published>2021-04-02T00:00:53+00:00</published><updated>2021-04-02T00:00:53+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blogs/2021/04/02/barriers-to-involvement-young-people</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blogs/2021/04/02/barriers-to-involvement-young-people.html">&lt;div class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/stock/young-people.jpeg&quot; style=&quot;width: 100%; height: auto;&quot; alt=&quot;A young girl and two women at a Labour Party rally in GE2019&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;image-bottom&quot;&gt;
    A young girl and two women at a Labour Party rally in GE2019  |  Credit @jeremycorbyn
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2021, Labour Nexus held a workshop with Young Labour members titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kw_stapleton_/status/1367916364946636802?s=20&quot;&gt;“How Can We Get Our Friends More Involved Despite Our Party’s Internal Culture”&lt;/a&gt;, where we discussed why Labour-supporting young people, including Young Labour members who are not very active in the party and its networks, do not get more involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The young people at our workshop identified the following issues with Young Labour that they felt were barriers to themselves or their friends getting more involved. We have typed them up to create this resource, which you are free to use and share if you credit us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Endless feuds — particularly local ones.&lt;/b&gt; Our workshop agreed that, separately to large-scale factional conflict, many activists had long-term personal grudges and rivalries with other activists, often based in past events. They felt this was a particular problem in CLPs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Antisemitism.&lt;/b&gt; Antisemitism in Labour, which everyone agreed continues to be a problem, was discussed as a barrier for Jewish people and for other potential members who did not wish to be associated with an antisemitic organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bland leadership.&lt;/b&gt; The young people at our workshop said that a barrier to getting their friends involved was that their friends had no idea what Keir Starmer stood for and saw him as “bland”, and as “uninspiring” relative to Jeremy Corbyn. One person also brought up the shadow cabinet and felt they had been too “quiet.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Corbyn “backstab”.&lt;/b&gt; Two people mentioned that their friends had said they were unwilling to get involved with Young Labour because Jeremy Corbyn had been “backstabbed” by Keir Starmer when he withdrew the whip in October 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Supporting Labour — which bit?&lt;/b&gt; One person pointed out that while “supporting the Tories” had a clear meaning, “supporting Labour” was likely to elicit the question “which bit of Labour?” No-one was sure what common values or policies united the various factions in the party and they agreed that made them feel that “supporting Labour” was vague.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Time-consuming.&lt;/b&gt; Being an active Young Labour member was perceived as time-consuming and potentially incompatible with studying for exams or working full time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Being involved requires politics knowledge.&lt;/b&gt; It was suggested that people might assume that to be an active member of Young Labour they had to be “politics nerds” with extensive knowledge and awareness of UK politics or Labour’s factions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Internal debates too economic-focused.&lt;/b&gt; One person said that they felt debates within Labour and the main points of disagreement between factions all focused on economics, whereas Tories and Lib Dems were more interested in debating social policy. Debates about social policy, they said, were more accessible than debates about economic policy, because the latter required technical knowledge about economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Policies not known.&lt;/b&gt; There was a shared perception that no-one knew any Labour policies, which made it hard to campaign for the party or be passionate about it in government. Only one person in the group, the discussion facilitator, could name a Labour policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Twitter, WhatsApp, TikTok.&lt;/b&gt; The group felt that being properly involved in Young Labour required using either Twitter, WhatsApp or what they called “cringe political TikTok”, which meant that encouraging someone to get involved meant persuading them to use one of those platforms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kerry Stapleton</name></author><category term="Blogs" /><summary type="html">A young girl and two women at a Labour Party rally in GE2019 | Credit @jeremycorbyn</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/stock/young-people.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/stock/young-people.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Introducing Alba Nexus</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/announcements/2021/04/01/defecting-to-alba-party.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing Alba Nexus" /><published>2021-04-01T00:00:53+00:00</published><updated>2021-04-01T00:00:53+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/announcements/2021/04/01/defecting-to-alba-party</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/announcements/2021/04/01/defecting-to-alba-party.html">&lt;p&gt;…..xczczxc&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Labour Party is riddled with factionalism and we see no reason to fix it. Instead, we are defecting to the one party in UK politics with no link to factions or party civil wars. The one political force which is devoted to our values of co-operation and working in good faith. The growing alliance of men and women fighting for the #Supermajority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; That’s right. We are defecting to the Alba Party. &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alex Salmond has decided to put his well-publicised differences with Nicola Sturgeon aside to — as he puts it — “help her” achieve a #Supermajority. How laudable. Indeed, we believe that launching the Alba Party was, in a sense, the ultimate act of anti- factionalism. There is no-one in modern British politics who dislikes petty squabbles, personal vendettas and unfounded conspiracy theories as much as Mr Salmond does. That is why we are proud to announce &lt;b&gt;Alba Nexus, uniting for the #Supermajority.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alba Nexus aims to “help” Mr Salmond and the Alba Party just as he hopes to “help” Ms Sturgeon and the SNP. We shall be the Alba Party’s very own Alba Party, uniting for the #Supermajority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some — most — all — of the Alba Nexus executive are based in England and Wales, but that sort of thing doesn’t seem to bother the Northern Independence Party, so we don’t see why it should bother Alba either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first campaign will be calling for a special conference to elect a new Alba leader who has a better track record on literally anything.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kerry Stapleton - Chair</name></author><category term="Announcements" /><summary type="html">…..xczczxc The Labour Party is riddled with factionalism and we see no reason to fix it. Instead, we are defecting to the one party in UK politics with no link to factions or party civil wars. The one political force which is devoted to our values of co-operation and working in good faith. The growing alliance of men and women fighting for the #Supermajority. That’s right. We are defecting to the Alba Party. Alex Salmond has decided to put his well-publicised differences with Nicola Sturgeon aside to — as he puts it — “help her” achieve a #Supermajority. How laudable. Indeed, we believe that launching the Alba Party was, in a sense, the ultimate act of anti- factionalism. There is no-one in modern British politics who dislikes petty squabbles, personal vendettas and unfounded conspiracy theories as much as Mr Salmond does. That is why we are proud to announce Alba Nexus, uniting for the #Supermajority. Alba Nexus aims to “help” Mr Salmond and the Alba Party just as he hopes to “help” Ms Sturgeon and the SNP. We shall be the Alba Party’s very own Alba Party, uniting for the #Supermajority. Some — most — all — of the Alba Nexus executive are based in England and Wales, but that sort of thing doesn’t seem to bother the Northern Independence Party, so we don’t see why it should bother Alba either. Our first campaign will be calling for a special conference to elect a new Alba leader who has a better track record on literally anything.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/stock/albanexusthumbnail.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/stock/albanexusthumbnail.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">You have a future, and you are worthy. 🌹 - An inspirational speech by Dawn Butler.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/video/2021/01/31/you-have-a-future-and-you-are-worthy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="You have a future, and you are worthy. 🌹 - An inspirational speech by Dawn Butler." /><published>2021-01-31T08:03:53+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-31T08:03:53+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/video/2021/01/31/you-have-a-future-and-you-are-worthy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/video/2021/01/31/you-have-a-future-and-you-are-worthy.html"></content><author><name>nexuslabour</name></author><category term="Video" /><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/posts/video/authenticself/thumbnail.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/posts/video/authenticself/thumbnail.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Ramsay MacDonald - The first Labour government 🌹</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/video/2021/01/26/first-labour-gov.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ramsay MacDonald - The first Labour government 🌹" /><published>2021-01-26T09:03:53+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-26T09:03:53+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/video/2021/01/26/first-labour-gov</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/video/2021/01/26/first-labour-gov.html"></content><author><name>nexuslabour</name></author><category term="Video" /><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/posts/video/first-labour-gov/thumbnail.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/posts/video/first-labour-gov/thumbnail.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A new COVID patient being admitted every thirty seconds. How did we get here?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/video/2021/01/17/A-new-covid-patient-every-thirty-seconds.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A new COVID patient being admitted every thirty seconds. How did we get here?" /><published>2021-01-17T09:03:53+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-17T09:03:53+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/video/2021/01/17/A-new-covid-patient-every-thirty-seconds</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/video/2021/01/17/A-new-covid-patient-every-thirty-seconds.html"></content><author><name>nexuslabour</name></author><category term="Video" /><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/posts/video/anewcovidpatient/thumbnail.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/posts/video/anewcovidpatient/thumbnail.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">These are Labour’s achievements since 1997</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/video/2021/01/17/Labour-Achievements-Since-1997.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="These are Labour’s achievements since 1997" /><published>2021-01-17T08:03:53+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-17T08:03:53+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/video/2021/01/17/Labour-Achievements-Since-1997</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/video/2021/01/17/Labour-Achievements-Since-1997.html"></content><author><name>nexuslabour</name></author><category term="Video" /><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/posts/video/LabourAchievements/thumbnail.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/posts/video/LabourAchievements/thumbnail.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">It’s up to us.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/video/2021/01/16/its-up-to-us.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="It’s up to us." /><published>2021-01-16T08:03:53+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-16T08:03:53+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/video/2021/01/16/its-up-to-us</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/video/2021/01/16/its-up-to-us.html"></content><author><name>nexuslabour</name></author><category term="Video" /><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/images/posts/video/itsuptous/thumbnail.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/images/posts/video/itsuptous/thumbnail.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A statement against transphobia following Dr Heather Peto’s resignation from LGBTQ+ Labour</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/statement/2020/11/29/a-statement-on-transphobia-copy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A statement against transphobia following Dr Heather Peto’s resignation from LGBTQ+ Labour" /><published>2020-11-29T08:03:53+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-29T08:03:53+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/statement/2020/11/29/a-statement-on-transphobia%20copy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/statement/2020/11/29/a-statement-on-transphobia-copy.html">&lt;p&gt;Labour has a problem with transphobia. The fact that Dr Heather Peto had to resign the chair of LGBTQ+ Labour today is an alarming sign of just how serious this problem has become, and it must be a call to stronger words and stronger actions — including from the party leadership, whose silence on transphobia in Labour is quickly becoming alarming as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nexus opposes transphobia in all its forms. This includes transphobia in the guise of debate — Nexus exists to promote co-operative debate in Labour, but we want to be absolutely clear that trans rights are not up for debate. Trans rights are human rights. If that statement is contentious for you, listen to trans voices and educate yourself, or leave.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>nexuslabour</name></author><category term="Statement" /><summary type="html">Labour has a problem with transphobia. The fact that Dr Heather Peto had to resign the chair of LGBTQ+ Labour today is an alarming sign of just how serious this problem has become, and it must be a call to stronger words and stronger actions — including from the party leadership, whose silence on transphobia in Labour is quickly becoming alarming as well.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/brand/default.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/brand/default.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>